<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Billy Messenger - Misc</title>
    <subtitle>The blogs I&#x27;ve written while developing audio software</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://billydm.github.io/tags/misc/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://billydm.github.io/"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://billydm.github.io/tags/misc/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>2024 Update</title>
        <published>2024-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://billydm.github.io/blog/2024-update/"/>
        <id>https://billydm.github.io/blog/2024-update/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://billydm.github.io/blog/2024-update/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;preface&quot;&gt;Preface&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, I&#x27;m back with something to show you! I&#x27;m sorry it&#x27;s been a while. I feel like I should explain what&#x27;s been going on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-i-was-doing-the-past-year&quot;&gt;What I was doing the past year?&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past year has been kind of rough for me. I haven&#x27;t gotten quite as much stuff done as I would have liked to. But I suppose mental and physical health come first. It&#x27;s taken me much longer to regain my footing than I thought it would.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;clarifying-some-things&quot;&gt;previous blogpost&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I said I was teaming up with someone who was creating a DAW with a GUI in Flutter that had a sort of similar timeline workflow vision. In a different universe where I was a different kind of person, this would have been an great opportunity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as it turns out, it&#x27;s taken me a long journey to realize I truly stay motivated best on large projects when working alone towards a highly specific vision. As a DAW user myself, GUI is very important to me. If I&#x27;m going to be doing this as my career, I want the GUI to be as good as I dream of having it. Otherwise I just don&#x27;t find the motivation to keep at a multiple-year long project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s not to say I don&#x27;t want other people working on Meadowlark. Just that I figured it&#x27;s best to only delegate tasks to other people that don&#x27;t involve core architecture stuff. I do still very much want help for other tasks like DSP, themes, samples, presets, and other various add-ons. I&#x27;m by no means an expert at DSP or sound design.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also ultimately decided against Flutter because I want a library that can also be used to make audio plugins that can be loaded into any DAW, not just Meadowlark. Flutter just doesn&#x27;t work for plugins &lt;em&gt;(see my previous blogpost &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;daw-frontend-development-struggles&quot;&gt;DAW Frontend Development Struggles&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for why)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. While there&#x27;s nothing wrong with existing plugin-compatible libraries like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;vizia&#x2F;vizia&quot;&gt;Vizia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;iced-rs&#x2F;iced&quot;&gt;Iced&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;emilk&#x2F;egui&quot;&gt;egui&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I would love it if I can have the same framework for both Meadowlark and my plugins. And since I need a solution for Meadowlark anyway, I finally just said screw it, I&#x27;m going to create my own GUI library and tailor the features I need and want. And who knows, maybe other people will find my GUI library useful too, or maybe it can inspire improvements in other GUI frameworks in some way?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know making a GUI library is very difficult and time consuming. But I&#x27;m not entirely new to this. I&#x27;ve had attempts at a simple GUI library in Rust in the past, and I have some past experience with graphics programming. In a future blogpost, I&#x27;ll explain how I&#x27;ve devised a way to keep the GUI library implementation as simple as possible while still achieving high performance and flexibility.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other Rust GUI libraries, mine does not aim for &quot;elegant and hard to misuse&quot;. It does not aim to be a &quot;general purpose&quot; GUI library with lots of features. It only contains the features I need. It&#x27;s not even declarative (although in theory you could write a declarative wrapper around it like what &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;Relm4&#x2F;Relm4&quot;&gt;Relm4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; does).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What my GUI library does give you is lots of manual control over how your widgets are structured, styled, and laid out. It&#x27;s sort-of a fusion between some of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;iced-rs&#x2F;iced&quot;&gt;Iced&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27;s concepts and traditional retained-mode GUI library concepts (although without the whole multiple-inheritance object-oriented thing). It uses a sort of &quot;I know where things should go&quot; and &quot;no hidden control flow or fancy macro magic&quot; philosophy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;coming-up&quot;&gt;Coming Up&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;rootvg&quot;&gt;next blogpost&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I&#x27;ll share a piece of what I accomplished. It&#x27;s a hardware-accelerated 2d vector graphics rendering library called RootVG!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in case you&#x27;re wondering, no I haven&#x27;t spent this entire time on just RootVG. I&#x27;m also getting closer to completing the GUI library as well. Stay tuned for that too!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
